Finding Aid for Orlan W. Boston papers, 1911-1959
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Orlan W. Boston papers 1911-1959
Boston, Orlan W. (Orlan William), 1891-
21 linear feet
85770 Aa 2
Professor of mechanical engineering, University of Michigan. Correspondence, committee reports, annual reports, and other papers, relating to the College of Engineering and to Boston's activities in professional societies; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Professor Boston (donor no. 295 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Orlan W. Boston was born in western Michigan, July 16, 1891. He received all his engineering education at The University of Michigan, with the degrees of BME 1914, MSE 1917, and ME 1926. He was professor of mechanical engineering and chairman of the Department of Production Engineering. He began his teaching career at the U-M in 1914 with an instructorship in engineering mechanics and mechanical engineering. In 1917, he was commissioned in the U.S. Naval Reserve where he was responsible in part for the design and manufacture of submarine mines in the Bureau of Ordnance. He served until 1919. For the next two years, Boston was industrial engineer and assistant to the vice-president and works-manager of the Cleveland Tractor Company.
He returned to the University of Michigan in 1921 as assistant professor. He was assigned to plan the south wing of the East Engineering Building and to develop courses and laboratories for Metal Processing, later known as Production Engineering. He was promoted to associate professor and acting director in 1923 and to professor and director in 1926.
Boston wrote several books dealing with production equipment, processes and materials, including Metal Processing. Several engineering handbooks, including Mark's Mechanical Engineering, contain sections prepared by Boston on machine tools, machinability and metrology. He retired from The University of Michigan in July, 1956. He died February 17, 1991.
The collection, largely unprocessed, has been maintained in the order received. There were three recognizable series: Professional Correspondence, dating from 1924 to 1956; Miscellaneous University Files; and Miscellaneous Correspondence (which covers roughly the same period as the Professional Correspondence but which Boston maintained separately). There is also one folder of photographs.
Subjects:
Boston, Orlan W. (Orlan William), 1891-1991; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Boston, William.; University of Michigan--Bands.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Engineering. Class of 1913.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Engineering. Class of 1914.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae--Anniversaries, etc.; University of Michigan. Senior Swingout.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Professional Correspondence
  - 1924-1941
    - A-F (Box 1)
    - G-O (Box 2)
    - P-Z (Box 3)
  - 1942-1943
    - A-Z (Box 4)
  - 1944-1945
    - A-F (Box 4)
    - G-Z (Box 5)
  - 1946
    - A-Z (Box 5)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 5)
    - A-O (Box 6)
    - P-Z (Box 7)
  - 1949-1950
    - A-K (Box 7)
    - L-Z (Box 8)
  - 1950-1951
    - A-T (Box 8)
    - U-Z (Box 9)
  - 1952
    - A-Z (Box 9)
  - 1953
    - A-Z (Box 10)
  - 1954-1955
    - A-E (Box 10)
    - A-Z (Box 11)
  - 1955-1956
    - A-E (Box 11)
- Miscellaneous University Files
  - Committee reports, also material on societies (Box 12)
  - Committee reports, also material on societies (Box 13)
    (continued)
  - Committee reports, also material on societies (Box 14)
  - Annual reports 1922-1949; budget, 1920-1949 also material on war surplus equipment (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous correspondence
  - circa 1930-1941
    - A-Am (Box 16)
    - Am-Ca (Box 17)
    - Ca-En (Box 18)
    - En-H General (Box 19)
    - Ha-Na (Box 20)
    - Na-Ro (Box 21)
- Photographs
  - Photographs 1911-1914, 1921, 1953, 1959 (Box 21)
    Photographs include prints of University of Michigan football games, Freshman-Sophomore Rush, Senior Swingout, and other student activities; reunion pictures of the Engineering Classes of 1913 and 1914 and a portrait of William Boston